And so the meeting is starting. I'm
going to admit everybody it usually
takes a minute or so for everybody to
come on in. And so we will get that
started. So uh good afternoon or good
evening everyone depending on how you
prefer to refer to this time of day. Uh
this is Dominic Earlo with the New
Mexico Department of Health and we're
just here um to help support Dezba with
the equity, access, and cultural
considerations committee. And so we will
be here to help uh from a department of
health standpoint. And just uh to let
everybody know, we do have a few people
from the department who are here. We
have Jorge Gonzalez, who is our program
manager for the medical psilocybin
program. Kathy Ojiri who is our project
manager for our center on medical
cannabis and psilocybin. Robert Truckner
who is our medical director. Uh Ishmael
uh Zutat who is our one of our health
educators with the program and is going
to be helping with regard to unmuting
and muting individuals for the public
comment and for the commentary area. Um
and then with that I will turn it on
over to you Desba. Um, thank you and
glad to see everybody here this evening.
The floor is yours, Despa. Your your
committee and your meeting.
>> All right. Hi, Yate. Hi, everyone. Um,
it's been a a um huge slide into today
is starting the first day of New Mexico
legislation for the 30 days. Um, so that
was that's how I started the day. Um and
with that, you know, we want to make
sure that um we're kind of just creating
a container and an environment for
everyone at this point to just um
provide input. We really want to provide
input. So um as we're creating these
meetings for all of the committees um
and including mine, um we also just want
to encourage more people to get
involved, more input. We have heard from
a number of different um sides. We're
looking at both the let's just say
recipient of the medicine, the patients
and also the facilitator, also the
propagation and cultivators um who are
going to be creating this um medicine
for New Mexicans. There is a lot to
uncover. Um we have especially in in the
context of equity, access and cultural
considerations. For those of you who are
not familiar with what's going on, we do
have a tribal liaison um in the
department of health who was going to be
facilitating uh reaching out to all the
tribal governors. There are uh 21
22 some of the PBLO governors and they
change every year. Um so we're still
kind of getting um up to date with that.
We also have the Apache tribes. We also
have the Navajo Nation. So, we are going
to hopefully be able to get input from
the tribal leaders that is not um
that is not like on the back burner. It
is something that's the forefront, but
we also want to make sure to addressing
rural communities, all access, all
different areas, cities and towns and
municipalities of uh New Mexico. And we
definitely are looking into how we can
address this on both the facilitator
administration administrator side as
well as the um individuals who are
requiring and needing um this medicine.
And with that we are looking at how can
we look at um insurance. Is insurance
going to be able to um be a factor in
this? Does it need to? Yes. Um, but this
is all information for you to also make
sure that New Mexico hears that. Um, how
is it going to be paid with the equity
fund? Um, what are those patient? What
does that patient look like? Um, you
know, from people I always keep saying
ma because that's up north where I'm
originally in that area up in the north.
Um but we also need to make sure that
anyone even in Los Cusus or Farmington
or uh Rudoso Raton um Portales um all
these places and especially the hardh
hit communities um as I know Rioba
County has steadily still continued to
have uh overdose overdoses on fentinyl
use um as well as Santa Fe County has
increased I think up to like 130% from
last year. this is beginning of last
year and also to believe house and so
these are things that we need to address
but how can we address them and I feel
like it is through community I know
that's a little bit off topic but I want
to use this time to really just if
there's anybody we're going to do a
listening session again um what I think
that I'm going to be doing is having um
staggered meetings where it is in the
evenings and it is also during the day I
know some people are you know we can't
all be on the same time time format. Um,
and I think it's really important that
we are if it's equity, access, and
cultural considerations that we really
are open to um the different communities
and and working backgrounds that we
have, especially if you know some of us
are pulling two and three jobs at a
time. Um, so just to recap a little bit,
I kind of sort of just threw a bunch of
stuff out you at you. Um, people have
brought up insurance. I want to have
these conversations about its
importance, paying for this, what it's
looking like with rural communities
before we actually start getting into
recommendations. We do have a short time
period and a time frame of less than a
year at this point. Um I'm looking to
kind of get some more movement in these
recommendations to uh the board um
probably within the next couple of
months whether it's um issues of
tellaalth how does that look when it
comes to rural communities um
and also the cost because it's not just
about the cost for the patients it's
also the cost for training education on
the side of um facilitators
and um what that training is look like.
Do the trainers are is the train um are
the people who are going to be trained
have that same access um to those
trainings? And so what I'm understanding
as far as equity, access, and cultural
considerations is how does it intersect
with all the other committees when it
comes to patient um care, when it comes
to propagation, when it comes to um end
of life care, that this is really truly
equitable and we're able to um have this
medicine available to all New Mexicans
who wish and seek to have access to it.
And what does that look like?
Um,
okay.
Let's see. Uh,
and also that I know we don't really
necessarily have to have bylaws, but I
do feel like we um I'm working on them.
Um, coming to some agreement and
consensus about how we're going to be
voting. I definitely appreciate outside
um input, and by outside, I mean outside
of New Mexico. Um I think that you know
two heads are better than one and
especially when it comes to Oregon and
Colorado who have already um been
dealing with this anyone even u with
research or input from New York or any
other place is also very valuable and
important. Um, and so your concerns and
input is important, but when it comes to
making sure to take care of New Mexicans
here within our uh, governance, um, we
need to be able to have a consensus of
who is being able to vote on a
recommendation that will then move to
the board for adoption into its
regulations and more formalized.
So I am working on that. I promised I
said I was going to it was going to be a
little bit more structured, but I
apologize about not having it structured
again today. And again, since it's only
about an hour long, I really would like
for anyone to um has anything to start
off the conversation.
And I again I would just uh really want
other people to um start bringing in
attend also the other meetings and see
where all of this looks at looks
like going forward. Um I we've we I've
noticed that in the research that that
is going to be starting to move. Um
uh all of these different all of the
information that we have when it comes
to these different committees is going
to inform the other one with research as
we progress and as we move forward is
going to inform um what kind of research
that we're going to do, what kind of
funding that's going to look like and so
forth.
Um all right, is there anybody who wants
to go ahead and speak up? I know we have
a couple of comments in the chat. Um,
and also another thing that I'm hoping
to be able to do essentially as well is
to have some in-person meetings. Um, I'm
not going to make a promise. This is
something that I am thinking about um
what it would look like to actually go
into different communities
um and actually having um
input from people face to face um if
that's something that people would like
to have some kind offormational session.
But also just gathering like what are
the big um barriers for a specific
community whether it's stigma um the use
of psilocybin might be an educational
uh and access point um
and and what does that look like? I will
say from a personal point of view um
with with religious background or even
um
I would say political leanings etc.
Those types of things may be informing
what might prevent someone from thinking
and feeling safe enough to want to move
forward with this type of therapy and
what does that educational outreach look
like? and it could be completely
different um in one part of the state
than the other. Um and with that with
with that um in mind um working with the
tribal communities will be completely
different than it might be working with
a community out in Deming um where some
of these places may be more hard hit. So
one size does not fit all in terms of
what it's going to look like. Um, when I
was working for the Navajo Nation, we
had regulations from the East Coast
where the soil is more acidic and here
our soil is more alkaline. That's the
kind of thing I'm talking about where
one thing does not necessarily mean it's
going to work in another environment.
And so, what does that look like for
your community? um to have that
educational what needs to be presented
and how does this medicine need to be um
shared when it comes to having those
one-on-one connections?
Um
all right. Do I have anybody who has any
kind of input? Um, I know from the
beginning
I do want to stop talking at some point
if there's anybody who is interested and
having a concern and it could be
anything. I know um
from one of the other uh meetings before
that we might feel like we're not
supposed to say anything, but I also
because of the cultural considerations,
but I also want to provide
um this idea that it is a safe space um
even though this is being recorded, just
FYI, um this is a safe space to be able
to share what your own personal concerns
concerns are because if it's your own
personal concern or something that is on
your heart or on your mind to share that
might be something that is um
might be on someone else's mind and they
might also not be able to feel
comfortable enough to share it. But if
you're speaking up and speaking for
yourself coming from your perspective
it's very helpful when it kind of moves
the discussion along. And that in place
is what um I feel like education and
outreach will do is that when we're
connecting one-on-one with each other,
we're able to understand um
what what each of us needs.
Um another point of
concern is just the urgency. Um I know
some people might be a little um
concerned with the timeline and um what
that looks like. So, I think I hear
someone trying to speak.
>> Yeah, that was just myself letting to
know that we have two hands up. Um, one
is Estvan Hernandez. Um, let me know if
you'd like me to uh Yep. Okay, I will
unmute them. Um, just give me a second.
There we have it. Uh, Estean, um,
please, you may begin.
>> Good evening everybody. Uh, Desbella,
thank you so much for hosting and thank
you everyone from the Department of
Health. Uh, my name is Stevon Hernandez.
I am the president of the New Mexico
Micology Guild. Uh we're focused on
advocating for local mushroom farmers
primarily to start, but we do look to
expand our uh offerings and inclusion to
uh both testing facilities as well as
facilitators of psilocybin therapy. Um
we've been meeting quite a bit over the
past year to kind of discuss what we see
as potential concerns for the program.
And I would say the largest concern that
we share right now is the potential for
this entire you know sector of uh
healthier New Mexico to be taken over by
uh out of state or multi-corporate
excuse me multi-state organizations. Um
as such we found that the uh state of
Oregon had implemented a sunset clause
for their medical psilocybin program
which we would love to see here in New
Mexico. Uh essentially this sunset
clause gives uh New Mexico residents a
real chance and a first foot on the
ground for uh access and participation
within this space uh by limiting
participation for any sort of licensing
to New Mexico residents who have held
that residency for at least two years
for the first four years of pro the
program's implementation. Now those
exact figures may vary depending on our
needs here in New Mexico. But I think it
would be really important to offer uh
small businesses in New Mexico, New
Mexican entrepreneurs, folks who have
been doing all of this work on the
ground in the meantime to really have
the first shake at participating in this
program. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much for that. U we also
have uh Vincent Espinosa. Um so I'm just
going to unmute them. Uh Vincent uh you
have to unmute yourself and begin.
Just to let you know, Vincent, the uh
microphone icon is on the top right of
your screen. Uh you should see that and
click it and that should unmute your
mic. If you're having any difficulties,
please drop a um a comment in the chat
and we can probably try and get back to
you if if it's not successful.
That's not a problem. Vincent, what
we'll do is um when if you Let's see if
I So, it seems here I have enabled your
mic. So, um perhaps it might be a good
idea to try to leave the chat and to
jump back in. That seems to do the trick
a lot of the time. So, we it's not the
first time this has occurred. So, try
that out. See what happens. And uh when
you join back into chat, raise your hand
and I will be sure to answer that. How
does that sound?
Okay, fantastic.
We also have a uh hand up there from
Gregory Evans.
Gregory, I have allowed your mic. Please
begin when you're ready.
>> Yeah, I had to turn it off and turn it
on again.
Um,
yeah, just to give you a break, Desba.
I'm really curious to see how we can
I don't think I'm going to be able to
spend a ton of time in this group, but I
definitely want to
leverage it in the ways that like it can
excel
um in understanding the inter you
mentioned the interconnectedness
between the work groups and mapping out
the dependencies from deliverables that
are happening ac happening across a
timeline. I almost think that that that
this group could do a lot to
kind of track and and hold some of those
events that are happening
between the groups and and making
certain that like
known dependencies are are are
held accountable and documented and uh
discussed
coming to
a space of like unified understanding.
Um I'm curious if you have a minute and
there are no other hands if since this
is the first time I've attended this
group um if there is a list of
this group's requirements,
what our goals are for the end, like
what does success look like?
um or if we're just kind of like
figuring that out as we get started.
Thanks.
>> Thank you very much for that. And we
have Vincent, so I'm just going to allow
the mic. Vincent, please unmute and uh
begin.
>> Yeah, I don't know. Um is everyone able
to hear me? Perfect.
>> Yes.
>> Well, wonderful. Um thank you for
letting me join this meeting. I'm very
excited. Um, I am a a therapist uh and
an LCSSW and private practice. So, I'm
uh licensed in Colorado, Oregon, New
Mexico. And I'm actually going through a
training company's psilocybin
certification program. They're known as
Fluence. And I'm hoping to get my uh
Colorado license as a clinical
facilitator uh here towards the middle
of this year. So, I was really excited
to hear, you know, about all of these
developments in New Mexico. And I think
my purpose for being here is, you know,
I was born and raised in New Mexico. You
know, I was raised, you know, uh, very
poor on Medicaid. And I know how it is
to access services. It's very difficult.
And, you know, this is such a wonderful
healing medicine. and I've facilitated
sessions with clients uh you know uh
integration and and phri uh uh harm
reduction right and and I think it's
just so important that there's a way
that you know we uh make it possible for
people who uh can't afford this you know
to access this and also I think someone
had said earlier you know uh preventing
corporations and and multi-state
entities from coming in and making it
you too commoditized and unaffordable.
So, um, that's kind of, you know, why
I'm here and, you know, that's what I'm
hoping to, you know, assist with. If I,
you know, can be a part of this in any
way, um, I would love to. And so, yeah,
thank you all for having me.
>> Thank you for that, Vincent. Uh, next we
have Aaliyah. Oh, your hand is down. I
don't know if you wanted to speak, but I
will allow your mic. If you wish to
speak, uh, please go ahead.
There may have been an accident on their
end. Okay, Desa, back to you. We have uh
no more hands up.
All right. So to the points of um that
Estavan has brought up and Greg um and
Vincent
um yeah to kind of starting off with
Greg's first though. Um yeah that there
are going to be a list of things. Um,
basically it's just it's going to look
almost similar to all the other
committees where we have like the
purpose and the responsibilities that
have been outlined already by um the
Department of Health and what the
committees are are meant to um
provide. Um, but then also how we're
going to be interacting. I just kind of
touched on it a little bit where we I do
encourage people from outside of New
Mexico to go ahead and speak up. Anybody
can speak up. um especially
I mean we've we've had a couple of
people who say that they don't want to
speak out of turn when it comes to
cultural considerations but we do have
people who have uh lived on the
reservation who are non-native um for
example and have their own
consideration for what that might look
like when it comes to um working um but
I feel that tribal governance is its own
separate thing that will require a
little bit more nuance and also with the
help of the tribal leaison as I had
mentioned earlier um to be able to
provide as I see it um the access and
the opportunity to be able to implement
it within their own governance as needed
as wanted um so that no agency is lost
between that and but I mean
self-governing agency um because we need
to respect that when it comes to
um the idea of indigenous wisdom to me I
feel like maybe this is lost a little
bit but it's almost inherent in the
medicine itself if we're making sure
that we are listening to the communities
that to me is inherent in indig
indigenous ancestral wisdom where we are
listening to the community and the needs
of the community in some ways it is
trying to find that balance balance
between a colonized mindset, well, this
is what you this is what we feel like is
necessary to to happen for the people as
a governance, right? Finding that
balance between what does it look like
um when we are listening to the needs of
the people and um also how we are going
to provide an environment governance um
so that we are able to have access to
every for everyone.
Um, and that to me is is is the equity
where
it's not just so much like what you're
able to
pay for, right? But we also need to be
able to moving into what um, Estean was
talking about is also taking care of our
own community, whether it's the
propagation culture cultivators and what
that looks like for them. Um as well as
how is it also being the the chain of
command
moving forward to get into the hands of
the facilitators, administrators
um and into the hands of of the um
patients for lack of a better
definition. And that's one of the things
we probably should also continue to
establish. But again, back to as um Greg
was saying with the intersection and as
I was mentioning, a lot of what I feel
like it's going to go back and forth.
Definitions are going to be um provided
to from the different communities and
what that looks like. Um, I feel like I
would probably propose, you know, this
idea of indigenous ancestor wisdom,
which I feel is a lot of what um, some
people are looking um to have a
definition of and understanding what
tribal governance and sovereignty is
also what also that looks like. Um, so
feel like we're not overstepping um, and
and and and out of our bounds and out of
our element when it comes to talking
about either or each. Um, I definitely
would like to have more indigenous um,
representation in the meetings, but then
that again that goes back to more people
providing the links and sharing this
information with as many people as
possible that these are the things that
we're looking at. Um, I know meetings
like this and even with it with the city
council here, I am in Santa Fe, it's
very hard to get people at the right
times um, either after work or during
work to be able to provide the input and
to have a voice. and this really is an
opportunity to share your voice and your
concerns and what it really means to
serve um our constituents and our fellow
community.
Uh what was the other thing that I was
trying to remember?
That was Estavon, Greg and Vincent with
Yes. Oh yeah, Esteon with the
regulations um and the sunset clauses.
That is something that we will
definitely be looking into because again
we're not trying to necessarily
uh say
we all understand that this is something
very new to New Mexico and our training
does not necessarily come from New
Mexico but we are looking into ways that
that um people who are going out of
state right um for their training what
that looks like but also that you So,
this is a great opportunity for
everybody. Um, and we'll we'll we'll
definitely look into those. So, as I'm
putting all of this information together
into something that can be voted on, as
far as recommendations
for regulations to the board, these are
some of the important um
concerns um that we will be eventually
voting on together and where again like
I hope that we can have um several
people involved in the process. process.
Um what it looks like is it might be
like a matter of at least you know a
simple majority depending on how many
people are actually attending and there
are going to be very a lot of a lot of
different committee um meetings
throughout and it's going to get uh your
head's going to start to spin like mine
if it hasn't already um to be able to be
a part of it. But back to the
intersection
um how we are helping inform the other
committees
when we're making sure that this is the
opportunity to voice up and say okay
uh patient care. Did we actually look
into this with regard to patient care?
Did we look at this in terms of end of
life care as a possible um example? Um
if there are elders who are on Medicaid
or any other elders who may not be able
to pay for
um you know
medicine, what does that look like? How
are they going to be able to have access
to it? And just making sure that the
language
um is in those recommendations and with
with respect to equity, access, and
cultural considerations.
Um and it could be anything. When I'm
thinking of end of life and what the
care looks like, I'm thinking of tribal
traditions. Um,
and I'm I'm just I'm just saying
something. I'm saying anything. Um, but
it could be all of these uh
considerations that we might have. Um,
and one more thing because I know we're
also running out of time again and I
spent my whole time talking. Um, one of
the reasons why I came back to New
Mexico to have my child when I was
living in Massachusetts was specifically
for the fact that New Mexico, um, labor
rooms allowed my family to be there with
me. Um, in Massachusetts, they said I
only was allowed two people in the
delivery room. And I said no to that. I
came home to New Mexico and I had my
child here because they understood that
um I could have as many people as I
wanted in the delivery room with me. I
was able to save the placenta for my
child being born and there was no one
who gave me any fuss about it. I didn't
have to explain myself. So these are the
kinds of places where cultural
considerations and western medicine can
intersect and why New Mexico is a unique
place for these types of things to
happen. And I want to have those um
considerations be a part of what it
looks like to be able to um partake in
this type of medicine. um whether it is
coming from um kurandas, massage
therapists,
therapists, uh lawyers, whatever it is
that we feel like the person who should
be able to provide um the access to this
medicine. And that's all up to you. It's
not necessarily up to me. I'm just here
with the microphone and the video camera
right now. But um we need to hear
everyone's thoughts on what that really
looks like. Um, and I can't do it alone
without the help of people providing
that input to what it looks like. Um,
otherwise I feel like it's just entirely
one-sided and it's just a soap box. It's
an opportunity for
uh any one agenda. Um, so I really need
all the different communities input and
that's why I was considering possibly
and with the um
um input of the Department of Health
whether or not it would be possible to
do some more in-person outreach um
hybrid um meetings and to possibly go
out into the rural areas, you know, time
permitting, and be able to just gather
that kind of information um and concerns
from from the mouths of of Mexicans. So
anyway,
um
>> we have a hand up there from Dominic
Zuro.
>> Dominic, please chime in. Tell me where
I'm
>> Thank you. No, no, no. You're you are
doing just fine, Despa. And you know,
some of the considerations you're
talking about, it's actually why I had
raised my hand. And some of it with
regard to in-person meetings we were
having some of these discussions as well
and we've brought it up in some of the
other meetings and some of the other uh
conversations that in person is great
and they absolutely can happen. We just
need enough time to schedule them
locations and places. We do have in the
chat there is actually one individual um
Deb Thornne who actually said that they
are willing to have to host in Los Cruus
for example uh and not that that's
necessarily a rural area of the state
but it's uh more accessible to people in
the southern areas of the states
especially the southwest area. So those
sort of things can happen. We just
recommend right now with the winter
weather to hold off on that, especially
in the more northern areas, but it's
good for the southern areas of the
state. Um, and um that as long as
they're hybrid, so people who may have
weather issues or not able even for
reasons other than weather are able to
attend um you know, because if there are
some people who are not able to travel
for whatever reason, they could then
still attend through virtual means.
We're happy to help set those on up and
we're willing to do that. We just need a
little time. We do also just recommend
that that not happen until after the
session because uh during the session um
any of us uh can and many of the people
who are involved in these committees can
get called to the roundhouse at any
time. Um and it also would um limit the
potential involvement of some of the um
sponsors of the bill who as most people
know are still very active and involved
in implementation. So that's the only
reasons we say wait but the session is
only a 30-day session. So, you know,
that means end of February, we could do
it, which if we want to set some of
those dates up, we can start working on
that and that's not a problem. Um,
because that'll give us time to be able
to do that. The other thing, and why I
actually had raised my hand initially,
is also that as a reminder, we have nine
positions for the board, but only seven
are filled. And so, we are actively
looking for other individuals to help
fill those other two positions. And we
especially would like to get
representation from uh communities that
have not yet been represented and
additional representation from ones that
have been under represented in the past.
Now that would be a lot to do with just
two positions, but we want to try to do
as best as we can. So we are actively
looking for individuals and if you are
interested in that um the qualifications
and the application are actually on the
advisory board web page and it is the
site I just put into the chat um and
that is www.nmhealth.org/aboutmcppab
org/aboutmcppab.
And if anybody has a way that we can
reduce those sort of letters, it would
be great. But again, it is in the chat
there for everyone. And so, uh, with
that, I'll turn it back on over. Thank
you everybody.
>> Thank you, Dominic. And um just yeah, so
please share that information with all
of your networks in your community.
Someone that you feel might um be a
really good candidate for that. We
really need more. I cannot emphasize
that enough. We need in order to be able
to create this network for um our
community. We need to um get the word
out and have these conversations that
may be kind of difficult for some of us
to continue to have or even to start. Um
but uh do like me. This is I'm the
example of getting out of your comfort
zone if anything is to just you know
find the time to talk to somebody um you
know that it it's just needed. I've seen
in I've seen enough and I've seen plenty
of instances where um I know I know that
this medicine works and the integration
process of it is um important and don't
forget that you are your own medicine
and you know don't forget your own power
when it comes to reaching out and
talking to others. Um regardless,
especially right now, um we need more
connection, more support, more
compassion, more love. Um let the
medicine do its work um within your life
when it comes to sharing that um to help
others get involved and the amount of um
concerns and input that we really need
from from you from from New Mexico. So
um with that I think I will conclude.
Um oh what kind of
>> it was just yeah
>> um what more input that I want um
just things to look out for. I know that
uh my I'm sorry. Well here's here's the
thing. My brain is so spun out from
being at the at the roundhouse earlier
today dealing with my 13-year-old and a
lot of uh the other stuff that um what
is the input? Don't don't forget about
X, Y, and Z when it comes to equity,
access, and cultural considerations.
Um with respect to medicine, the
psilocybin, um
what does it look like? I like I said
I've heard I've heard about insurance
teleaalth rule. Um what does that
education looks like? I guess maybe the
homework for anybody would be if you
were having a hard time trying to start
a conversation with someone about um the
benefits of psilocybin. What would that
look like? What what kind of educational
tools? And I'm not saying this is the
only one, but this is an example. what
would be an educational tool that would
be necessary and needed to help
facilitate that connection with another
person. Um to me that is providing
someone with the agency to choose on
their own if this is the right path for
them and what does that look like? And
if a barrier were was money then what
does that person need in that particular
area? How would they be able to get it
in might be different in Espanola than
it would be in Crown Point or even a
border a checkerboard um town Gallup.
We it might be a religious um barrier.
It could be a political barrier. It
could be a reading barrier. It could be
an accessibility barrier, right? Whether
or not it's someone who um
yeah, any any kind of accessibility uh
issue that might be a challenge. Okay.
So, Greg, you got a minute.
Oh, is that Aaliyah? Aaliyah list.
>> No, I just really quick like would it be
too remedial to just like start writing
a list
of disperate
sections of our society? Like like an
impossible task of course, but like
can we just
Yeah. equity is is is so broad and I
think like the the cultural
considerations
need to be in some way defined. It's
like what does espanola need? Like but
we have to define what an espanola is,
right? Espanola could mean this to one
person and that to another person and
tribal nations could be one thing in one
area and through another thing in
another area. And it's like how can we
start to like really just define what
the work is
um to provide access and access to
information
which is again like kind of that like
partner arm of the education module of
our of of of our board. Anyways, just
some thoughts.
>> Thank you for that. We also have
Aaliyah. Let me just try to uh allow
their microphone. Um,
when you're ready to speak, uh, please
unmute.
>> Hello. Can you hear me?
>> Mhm.
>> Yes.
>> Great. Um, hopefully I can get my
thoughts and
um,
working in a stream here. Um, I'm really
concerned also about the um
affordability and access to a really
broad spectrum of people in the state
and
I've read
part of the the bill
and looking at the what the qualifying
conditions are
um for depression and post-traumatic
stress disorder and substance abuse and
end of life care. But then it also
number five is other conditions approved
by the department
and I've heard a lot about you know so
that's pretty open as a potential
medical benefits and
mostly I hear about I've been hearing
about uh using
the um psilocybin in full doses but
there's such an incredible potential
benefit of micro ing and for a broad
spectrum of medical benefits and create
creates potentially creates a lot more
accessibility and affordability for for
a lot of people
be um if they're not required to I mean
because you're not feeling high from
micro doing
um if you're taking the right dose And
it doesn't, you know, people, so far
I've heard that even with my dosing, if
that's accessible that somebody would
have to have a care person there, but
that doesn't seem like it really makes
sense and or that it's not really need
necessary and and would make it more ex
make the medicine more available to a
broader spectrum of people. Uh some
people need the full dose, but some
people don't. And micro doing helps
people to be able to keep functioning in
their day-to-day life and they don't
have to be with a care person uh a
therapist for hours on end um or even
necessarily at all um unless something
comes up and then they contact a care a
therapist to support them. Um so I'd
really like to see the micro doing
brought into the picture more as well.
Um, and more talk about, you know,
having that be accessible without having
to go into a center and sit there for
hours or however long there is the board
decides is being required.
Um, anyway, uh, there's so much that can
people can benefit from that from micro
doing as well.
That's mainly what I wanted to say at
the moment. and I just wanted to bring
it into the conversation.
>> Thank you for that. Um, we also have a
hand up there by Liars.
Uh, so Eliva or Ellie. Um, pardon me if
I mispronounced it. Uh, I have unmuted
you. Um, please go ahead.
>> Thank you. And now you got it right the
first time. It's L. Um, you all can hear
me? Yes.
Yeah. Okay, cool. Um, so just hearing
some of like the um qualifications I
guess in order to access the medicine,
something that came up for me right away
was like being diagnosed even with
something like depression or PTSD and
like how and what that looks like in New
Mexico. Um, I've stated before when I've
been in this group that I am from New
Mexico, but I'm a social worker in New
York City. And I know out here like we
don't have very many providers to meet
the demand and weight lists are long.
And then also like thinking about who's
more likely to get a diagnosis and how
you have to present yourself in order to
get a diagnosis. Um, that's just
something I guess that like came up for
me. Um, and I don't know if that's like
too large of like a like this is a real
big systemic thing. Um, but it is
something that came came to mind uh to
me is like someone's ability to get a
diagnosis
like being a barrier also I think. Um,
and I wonder how we might be able to
sort of like negate that barrier or like
reduce it. But yeah, just thought I
would throw that one out there too.
Thank you for that. We have no more
hands up.
>> Um just a quick question on I missed the
part when for L. Um you were saying to
negate that barrier and my mind kind of
went for a second. Do you mind um saying
that over again? As far I know that what
I got was that there weren't very many
providers in New York City and it had to
do with um there was
how how how a patient or a client or a
person would present themselves to be
able to be diagnosed to and and I kind
of lost and I know we have a notetaker.
I totally get it. But this is just for
my um for me to hear what that again
about negating something barrier.
Yeah. I mean I'm not sure in this moment
necessarily like what the solution would
be, but in my experience there's like
two two things, right? So, one is the
demand being insanely high and there not
being enough providers and it taking a
really long time for someone to even get
seen by a provider, let alone receive a
diagnosis that would qualify them um to
be able to like have access to this sort
of medicine. Um so, that's one, right?
Like who who are the providers that can
provide diagnoses and why are there such
long wait lists and stuff to be able to
access those providers? And then two is
like, you know, the DSM was written by a
bunch of white men. And so like patients
have to present themselves in a certain
way a lot of times in order to obtain a
diagnosis. And particularly for women of
color, it can take longer and you have
to go through more providers in order to
get a diagnosis. So, those were just two
things that I was sort of thinking about
hearing like, oh, you have to be able to
have like depression diagnosed or PTSD
diagnosed. Like a lot of people self
diagnose themselves because getting that
diagnosis, there's a big barrier in that
in and of itself. Does that make sense?
>> Yeah. And I think that that since and I
apologize I completely forgot that we
don't end at six o'clock. I even got got
myself confused with my own time uh meet
my meeting time here. Um
what I'm hearing from you is and also
Aaliyah is an intersection of you know
what are other conditions
and how those two interact with each
other. Um, and just a little bit of a
reminder, while these are definitely
good points, especially
when it comes to looking at the
framework of medical psilocybin
that what we're trying to roll out at
the end of the year um, and Dominic can
definitely um, speak to this a little
more if you if he wants to, is um, how
do we get started? What is our starting
point so that we can move forward with
the possibility that it might move into
a place of people micro doing
um with their own agency? What what
could that possibly look like? I don't
feel like we're looking at that just
yet, but the starting framework is how
do we get started? And it might be to a
good point to what you're saying l
and this is like a cultural
consideration. This is the access and
equity of it is,
you know, what does that balance look
like and that ratio of providers to
patients? And um I'm not going to say
that we're going to get it right the
first time, but eventually, you know, is
there going to be an oversaturation of
mushroom cultivators and prop uh people
who are doing propagation? We don't also
want that either. Um I feel at least
this is my own personal opinion just to
say you know we want to make sure that
it is a viable source of income right
for the people who are providing it.
Some people may look down on that
because they feel like money should not
be exchanged right but also at the same
time um money is energy people people's
time is their energy and their love that
they put into creating the medicine for
people to share it with others. I think
in Colorado that was one of the things
you can share the mushrooms but no money
should be exchanged when it comes to
that but that's a completely different
different uh regulation.
Um but again it's like what's the
starting point and what are we looking
at these are the things that we do need
to be considerate of in the future. Um
and especially like they didn't start
diagnosing women with ADD. Uh right and
I totally understand that. until totally
get that women present completely
differently than men do. Um, kids even
present differently than adults do. Um,
especially when it comes to diagnosis.
So, that is something that is important
to look at. Um, I would encourage
Aaliyah to possibly try to find um the
dosage maybe just to listen in on the
dosage committee um patient care. Uh I
think it's there's there's there's
another one that Ian is the chair of but
dosage um is more probably going to be
medical but um also I think there is the
propagation like we're going to be
talking about this we're going to be
talking about the cultivars the
different types of mushrooms that may or
may not be available what does micro
dosing look like what are those
regulations what does a heroic dose we
all kind of agree on that but that also
can be depended dependent on the type of
mushroom that is being offered. Aborts,
for anyone who's familiar with that
term, might be massively more um potent
than their regular adult counterparts
and that might be completely different
and all of these things are going to
possibly be taken into consideration.
um someone's micro dose at a you know.3
grams milligrams is going to be
completely different than someone's one
gram um uh micro doing um some people
just are have a different um tolerance
than others but what does that look like
when we're kind of creating the
framework so all of this is definitely
important and it's worth considering and
hopefully that maybe even actually this
committee in and of itself is like the
information of where to go if you have a
concern turn because I'm I'm I'm doing
this at 5:00 and not everybody else can
be available at 11:00 or 9:00 and so I
don't mind being like go here, go this,
go talk to this person. That's a great
concern. Bring that up within, bring
this up with Chris, um and so forth. I
don't mind that that's like the
information highway and the, you know,
find out information here.
>> Just a quick one. Uh we have two hands
up there. Um
>> sure,
>> Melena Robbins. Uh, I have allowed your
mic. Please begin when ready.
>> Can you hear me? Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Okay, great. Thank you. Um, I would just
like to contribute the fact that New
Mexico borders
uh, Mexico and the we talked a little
bit about indigenous knowledge systems.
And if we think about um, the trade
routes, the ancestral trade routes that
have gone north to south for millennia,
for thousands of generations, and have
now been cut off by this political
border. um that the medicines are
traveling and they're wanting to engage
and they're wanting people to to
reinvigorate or re reawaken these trade
routes. And so I would I would um just
like to add the Masetch and um maybe
building some bridges there. Uh finding
Masetch organizations maybe the there's
Ini Lores Garcia. Um I think he's
working on a museum about Maria Sabina.
There's the um botanical dimensions. Um
just a quick even Google search uh the
fungi foundation has the ethnomiccology
ethical guidelines on how to engage with
indigenous peoples or engage ethically
with fungi knowledge. um and just sh I
can share these resources in the chat
but uh yeah I think when we're think
when we're talking about indigenous
knowledge systems and this is just a
scenario that I've been kind of playing
around with is say we say uh the Navo
Nation is asking for um a psilocybin
assisted therapy a culturally informed
psilocy psilocybin assisted therapy
model then what would it look like uh to
have traditional Hatashi medicine people
engage with uh Masate Kurandelas who
have knowledge about how to hold these
mushrooms in ceremony and and build a a
model that is taking into account um
teachings from the Masetch ceremony but
also teachings from D ceremony whether
that's language ceremony food systems
prayer um protocols practices and then
also the western therapeutic um model
and how do these systems of knowledge
engage engage, teach one another and
learn from each other because um I think
there's this balancing act between
indigenous indigenous science,
indigenous ways of knowing and then
western science and um western uh
dominant western paradigms of of
practice. So um how do we uh find an
equilibrium between the two?
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you for that. We have one last uh
hand up by Brett Phelps. Um
Brett, I've allowed your mic. Please
begin when ready.
>> Hey, good evening everybody. Glad to see
everyone here virtually again. Um just
one thing I wanted to to throw out for
this committee. you know, included in
the statute was the uh the equity fund,
the patient equity fund, um which was
created but was not um funded. And so um
any members of this committee would just
encourage you all, you know, the
legislative session has just started.
Um, and Dominic, if you have any
guidance on this, I don't know if DO is
is working on this as well, but
advocating to get some of that funding
from the legislature this year, um, I
think would be fantastic. You know, I
know I know we're all pretty busy, but
if anyone wants to, you know, go do that
up in Santa Fe, I would strongly
encourage it. I'll be up there trying to
to push for that and and get some funds
for that because it's currently not
included in the budget, at least the
latest I had seen. Um, but that's just
one thing I wanted to mention.
Otherwise, I I really like what this
group's doing and yeah, I'm happy to
keep working with y'all.
>> Fantastic. And Dominic, please go ahead.
>> Thank you, Brett, for bringing that up
as far as the equity fund. That actually
was a part of what Desbah was talking
about earlier as far as you know what
can we do with regard to ensuring equity
and access and when the the statute when
the bill was originally presented it was
with the equity fund with a million
dollars per year allocated towards it
and then that did end up getting taken
out. The fund was created but the
funding was removed. um it is not in the
current executive budget and for those
who are familiar with regard to what
state agencies can and cannot do I
cannot advocate one way or another for
it. However, the original idea and mind
you this is the original idea is that
equity fund would help especially with
regard to individuals in rural and
frontier areas to be able to help with
people who had transportation issues,
people who have historically been
neglected by the medical establishment
in being able to get treatment, whether
that be from a diagnosis standpoint all
the way through to treatment, therapy,
everything else. And so, uh, I do know
and and I don't mean to speak for him,
but I do know that Senator Steinborn,
who is the primary one of the primary
sponsors of the bill, was um really
trying to see what could be done with
regard to that aspect from uh from the
equity fund. So, the equity fund and the
research fund were both created, but not
funded during the original session.
Hopefully, we'll see some change in that
here in the future. But again, I can't
actually advocate one way or the other.
However, that does not stop any of you
from advocating one way or the other. I
just can't also tell you what to
advocate for with regard to the
legislature. So, how's that for walking
the line? Um,
anyway, uh, thank you everybody. I
appreciate it. I did just want to also
note that, you know, it's really
important to read through the full
statute to see what the statute allows
and does not allow because there are a
lot of great ideas and a lot of areas
that can be explored down the road in
the future. But the statute is pretty
clear as to what we can do and it really
to read through it and understand and if
there are questions about it uh we are
going in at some point in the not too
distant future actually have uh during
one of the meetings where we're going to
talk about exactly what can and can't be
done. But we don't want to disturb the
free flow of information and bias people
during this uh right now. And so just
let everybody know there that does
actually that is actually something that
we are looking at doing down the road so
that people have a better understanding
of what can actually be done under it.
And the important part about this is to
help us figure out ways to still improve
access and equity even with the
strictctures and the restrictions put on
us by the statute. Um but still staying
within the statute if that helps make
sense. And with that, thank you. Back to
you, Desba. I don't think there's
anybody else uh currently with their
hands raised.
>> No, but I I do want to um ask a couple
of questions on that, Dominic. um when
it comes to
allowing people to look up information,
when it comes to maybe organizations who
might have more information on what
they're looking for,
uh like the healing advocacy fund.
Um, I know I know that some people are
are working towards um uh
the language and talking to legislators
about it. Um, so I don't know what
information we can or cannot provide as
far as like it's out there um to talk to
the legislators and tell them uh what
you feel is is is important to you. you
meaning New Mexico um citizens. Um but
also to your point, I just kind for the
sake of saying so I mean for a lot of us
um who may be having done the work in in
this field for a really long time, a lot
of the longtime advocates
um just to be mindful um that there
might be some new people who are not
used to what the intersection of
government looks like when it comes to
these regulations. A lot of us have been
underground for quite some time and know
a lot of information, have a plethora of
knowledge when it comes to either
growing or set and setting and ceremony.
But that's also kind of where I feel
like the equity and the access does come
into consideration when I'm saying the
education part of it at least for me
when we're looking at it is what do the
new first comers need to have as far as
like this is something that is um
beneficial to their growth. Um and we
also can just learn something new all
the time. Um we may have been in stuck
in this framework for a really long time
when it comes to uh legalization
or when it comes to um only coming from
a coming at it from a western medical
point of view. Um we all have a bias. We
all have an agenda. We all have our um
preconceived notions about how things
should be done or what's the best way
and I just encourage that despite that
we really look at what it might also be
for those who have never had the
opportunity and those are also to the
people that I want to make sure that
this medicine reaches. So if maybe there
is a redundant question and we like to
Dominic's point, you know, at some point
we are going to start kind of, you know,
being a little bit more structured about
how we're going about this, what does it
actually really look like? Um, and I
don't want people to feel afraid of
voicing something that they feel is
really important. Um, again, to be, you
know, I'm from Santa Fe. I am coming
from this frame of mind is that it if we
were all thinking the same thing and
we're all seeing it from the same point
of view. There wouldn't be a reason to
have so many different voices. I feel
like it's just us experiencing,
you know, the beauty of the world
through each individual different
person. And so your thoughts and your
concerns and everything that you are
wanting to know and would like to know
um through your own prejudice or bias is
important. Um, and that's why I do want
to listen when it comes to what people
have to say. And even if it's something
that's that I may not hold dear to me or
that might be in opposition to someone
else, um, we don't get to work through
these things um, siloed and away from
each other. This is an opportunity to
grow not just um as individuals but
through this process of how do we take
care of each other with the government
involved um so that it is equitable and
yes that is a big word to chew um but
we're all doing our best and um I'm not
assuming that I know what's best and I
definitely appreciate all the input
whether or not it's coming from from a
place of quote ignorance or a prejudice
or a bias bias. Um that helps us learn
how we better need to communicate what
needs to be said and how it needs to be
presented so that we are all on the same
page eventually. Um and then we can go
further from there so that we can
implement some of these great ideas that
a lot of us have presented over the past
few weeks that may or may not actually
fall into the framework of medical
psilocybin governance that we are we're
trying to get um going at the be at the
end of the year.
Um
all right,
I have five minutes left.
Um I don't think anybody else has
anything else to say. if you want to get
like one last word in Dominic or anyone
else.
>> I just want to say thank you because
it's great to see the questions
especially in the in the chat and that
the different speakers have brought
forward because this this is exactly
what we need to hear. It's exactly what
we want to hear. We want those differing
viewpoints. We want to be able to figure
out how can we create the best program
that can reach the most people and
especially the people who need it. And
so it's really great to hear this. So
just thank you to everybody. And uh for
those who are wondering, there's
additional information being put in the
chat. Uh so thank you Deb uh Thorne for
posting those links and um and all of I
mean it's just really great. Um and as
far as posting broadly Greg, I can
answer that. Yes, you can. Uh, that's
just not something that the Department
of Health can do.
>> Yes, most of us
without the horns blurring.
All right. Well, thank you everybody.
Have a great evening. Get some dinner if
you haven't. Get some rest. Drink some
water. Uh, don't forget to take care of
yourselves because you're important.
Bye.